Holloman Family 041
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Holloman Family Papers
1915-1975
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Holloman, John L. S., Reverend
Holloman, Rosa
041
12 Linear feet
29 Boxes
Biographical / Historical
The Reverend John L. S. Holloman, native of Hertford County, North Carolina graduated from Waters Institute in Winton, North Carolina in 1905. Holloman attended Virginia Union Theological Seminary from 1906 to 1908 and then taught at Waters Institute from 1910 to 1917 while at the same time serving as pastor of a small rural church. In 1912 he married Rosa Victoria Jones, a native of Charlottesville and a graduate of Hampton Institute.
In 1917 the Hollomans moved to Washington, D.C. where Reverend Holloman became pastor of the famous Second Baptist Church of Washington, D.C. until his retirement. Second Baptist was noted for its Sunday School Lyceum, which became a magnet for leading intellectuals in the African-American community.
Reverend Holloman was President of the Washington Baptist Seminary since its founding in 1927 and President of the Board of Trustees of the Stoddard Baptist Home. Locally, he was active in civic organizations and the Republican Party. He gained a national reputation as editor of the Lott Carey Herald, official organ of the Lott Carey Baptist Foreign Mission Society. Mrs. Holloman at various times served as President of the Lott Carey Convention Women's Auxiliary as well as a leader in local and national organizations for minister's wives. She was an Eastern Star member of the Datcher Chapter and active in the PTA. The Holloman's children are Carolyn H. Troupe, Grace H. Davis, Jessie H. Jackson, Marjorie H. Parker, and Dr. J.L.S. Holloman.
Custodial History
The Holloman family children donated the papers to the Library in 1992.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist primarily of the correspondence of Reverend Holloman from the 1920s through the 1960s, years in which he served as pastor of the Second Baptist Church of Washington, D.C. Reverend Holloman's handwritten lecture notes and manuscripts of sermons, speeches, and articles are in the collection as well as some records from the Second Baptist church. Files regarding the Holloman's work in the Lott Carey Society, the National Baptist Convention, Eastern Star, Alpha Sigma Sorority and other religious and civic organization are in the papers. Also included are family photographs, a travel log, and other family memorabilia. The papers are arranged into five series: correspondence, Rosa Holloman materials, church records, sermons and writings, and family memorabilia.
City churches; Clergy; Religion; Speeches, addresses, etc; Correspondence; Organizational Records; Families; African Americans
- Series 1: Correspondence 1917-1967
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Reverend Holloman's professional and personal correspondence during his tenure at the Second Avenue Baptist Church. Reverend Holloman corresponded with ministers all along the east coast as well as officials in a variety of civic and religious organizations in D.C. and the nation. A sample of organizations represented in the correspondence include the Stoddard Baptist Home; The Shiloh Baptist Church in D.C.; Union Baptist Church in Stamford, Connecticut; Virginia Union Theological Seminary; the Metro Baptist Church in D.C.; and the Republican State Committee in D.C. The correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Untitled, 1915-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Misc., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Untitled, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1942-1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1947-1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Misc., 1940s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Untitled, 1950-1952 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1953-1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1953-1957 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1953-1957 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1953-1957 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1953-1957 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1958-1959 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Misc Correspondence, 1950s (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Untitled, 1960-1964 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1965-1969 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Misc., 1960s (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Rosa Holloman Materials, 1930-1971
  This series contains programs, publications, speeches, certificates, handwritten meeting notes, and publications which cover Mrs. Holloman's involvement in the Datcher Chapter of Eastern Star, Lott Carey Women's Auxiliary, Sigma Shadows of Alpha Sigma Sorority, and the National Association of Minister's Wives. It also includes Mrs. Holloman's correspondence and a handwritten account of the Holloman's trip to the Baptist World Alliance Congress held in London in 1955 with extended travel through Europe, Egypt, and the "holy land."
  - Rosa Holloman's correspondence, 1937-1971 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Ministers Wives, 1937-1971 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Rosa Holloman's speeches, 1955-1969 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Eastern Star, 1938-1957 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Alpha Sigma, 1938-1957 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Women's Auxiliary of Lott Carey, 1938-1957 (Box 19, Folder 3)
- Series 3: Church Records, 1915-1972
  Financial materials, including tax data, correspondence, insurance, receipts, and invoices appear first, arranged in chronological order. After the financial records, are other church records, including programs, newsletters, correspondence, attendance sheets, and award certificates which document the activities of the Second Avenue Baptist Church. The series also includes materials regarding Reverend Holloman's work for Lott Carey and the National Baptist Convention.
  - Second Baptist Weekly Bulletins, 1950-1970 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Funeral statements, 1965-1969 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Gold Everywhere (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Lott Carey materials, 1921-1958 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Church Finance/insurance/tax papers, 1947-1959 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Church Finance/insurance/tax papers, 1947-1959 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Church Finance/insurance/tax papers, 1947-1959 (Box 24, Folder 1)
- Series 4: Sermons and Writings, 1915-1972
  This series contains written manuscripts of many of Reverend Holloman's sermons, speeches, book reviews, journal articles, reports, editorials, and other writings.
  - Lecture/outlines/sermons, 1915-1972 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Speeches/articles/reviews/reports, 1915-1972 (Box 26, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Family Memorabilia, 1926-1963
  The series includes greeting cards, addressed envelopes, a calling card plate of Reverend Holloman, a travel log, a hood for a commencement gown, and school papers of 5th grader Jason Parker in 1953.
  - Greeting cards/envelopes, Undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
  - Address lists/birth registration/clippings/other misc., 1919-1972 (Box 27, Folder 2)
  - Travel log (trip to Europe and holy land), 1955 (Box 27, Folder 3)
  - Family papers and photographs, Undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Hood for gown, Undated (Box 29, Folder 1)